Guide to the Brooklyn Historical Society institutional records ARC.288
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 3: Executive Director files, 1965-1998
  - Sub-series 3.6: Irene Tichenor, 1996-1997
    Irene Tichenor was appointed Acting Executive Director by the Society's Board after the departure of David Kahn. Tichenor was not interested in keeping the position permanently and only held the position while the search continued for a new, permanent Executive Director. She held the position from 1996 until 1998.
    The bulk of Irene Tichenor's papers include correspondence, meeting minutes, and educational materials, most of which surround the subject of hiring a new director and the building renovation project.
    - Correspondence, 1996 November (Box 707)
    - Correspondence: Invitations, 1996-1997 (Box 707)
      Includes invitations from American Red Cross, Brooklyn Tech, Herbert E. Berman, Brooklyn Heights Garden Club's holiday tree lighting, Howard Golden, Kenneth K. Fisher, and New-York Historical Society.
    - Subject Files, 1996-1997 (Box 707)
      Includes files for C.W. Shaver, Management and Funding Plan, Priority (Director search, meetings, NEH grant, construction), Search for Executive Director, and Transition Team.
- Series 4: President files, 1944-2020
  The title of President originally referred to the head of the Board of Directors. This position lasted with that title from the inception of the Long Island Historical Society in 1863 until 1999.
  When the By-Laws were changed in 1999, the title of "President" no longer referred to the head of the Board (that title became the "Chair"). The title of "President" became the title for the former Executive Director position. All presidents after 1999 were the heads of the Brooklyn Historical Society, not the Board. Carol Clark held the role at that time of the title change and, according to Jessie Kelly's oral history, was the one who pushed for the change.
  Despite the difference in the positions of President of the Board and President of the Brooklyn Historical Society, these files are kept together because of their use of the same title.
  These files are arranged first according to the president to whom they were either created by or for, or were utilized by during their tenure. From there, the files are arranged alphabetically according to subject, then arranged chronologically.
  - Sub-series 4.1: William B. Davenport, 1929
    - [Note from Society of Old Brooklynites], 1929-10 (Box 729)
      The note is misaddressed to a "John B. Davenport"; there was no John Davenport who was president of the Long Island Historical Society. However, William B. Davenport's ancestor was notably Reverend John Davenport, founder of New Haven colony.
  - Sub-series 4.2: B. Herbert Smith, 1938
    - 75th Anniversary, 1938 January (Box 729)
  - Sub-series 4.3: Guy du Val, 1944-1948
    Guy du Val was the President of the Board of Directors of the Long Island Historical Society from 1939 until 1949.
    - [Correspondence with William Robbins], 1943 February (Box 729)
    - [LIHS member newsletter], 1944 July-1948 (Box 729)
    - [Long Island Historical Society articles], undated scan; original published 1925 January (Box 729)
    - Schenck House, Highland Park, 1941 April-May (Box 729)
  - Sub-series 4.4: Lewis W. Francis, 1951
    The two folders in this sub-series are arranged alphabetically by topic.
    Lewis W. Francis was the President of the Board of Directors of the Long Island Historical Society from 1949 until 1951.
    Lewis W. Francis's papers include LIHS Newsletters and a Certificate of Report of Existence for the Long Island Historical Society issued by the State of New York.
    - Certificate of Report of Existence, 1951 February (Box 729)
    - [LIHS member newsletter], 1949 September-1951 June (Box 729)
    - [George Washington birthday celebration], 1932 January-February (Box 729)
    - [Correspondence, newsletters, and pamphlets], 1949 November-1951 May (Box 729)
  - Sub-series 4.5: Joseph Dana Allen, 1956 (Box 729)
    Joseph Dana Allen was the President of the Board of Directors of the Long Island Historical Society from 1952 until 1957.
    This sub-series consists of a single folder containing the June 1956 LIHS member newsletter.
  - Sub-series 4.6: Edgerton G. North, 1957-1964
    Edgarton G. North's papers are organized into Correspondence and Subject Files. The correspondence is arranged chronologically. The subject files are arranged alphabetically.
    Edgarton G. North was the President of the Board of Directors of the Long Island Historical Society from 1957 until 1965.
    Edgarton G. North's papers include correspondence, loan applications, a survey of LIHS, and LIHS policy.
    - Correspondence, 1957-1964 (Box 729)
    - Subject files
      - Loan Applications, 1959 June (Box 729)
      - [LIHS member newsletters], 1957 June - 1959 October (Box 729)
      - LIHS policy, undated (Box 729)
      - Survey of LIHS, undated (Box 729)
  - Sub-series 4.7: William R. Fisher, 1974 (Box 729)
    William R. Fisher was the President of the Board of Directors of the Long Island Historical Society from 1974 until 1975.
    William R. Fisher's papers include a memorandum to the Board of Directors, a list of LIHS Directors, meeting minutes, and correspondence.
  - Sub-series 4.8: Dwight B. Demeritt, Jr., 1967-1978
    Dwight B. Demerrit, Jr.'s papers are arranged alphabetically by topic.
    Dwight B. Demeritt, Jr. was the President of the Board of Directors of the Long Island Historical Society from 1978 until 1980.
    Dwight B. Demerrit, Jr.'s papers include materials relating to the 114th Annual Dinner, Battle of Long Island research, the Missouri Historical Society, and Raymond Chambers and the Camberwell Collection.
    - 114th Annual Meeting and Dinner, 1978 February - May (Box 730)
    - Battle of Long Island, 1967 September - 1968 January (Box 730)
    - Missouri Historical Society, undated (Box 730)
    - National Maritime Historical Society and Sloop Clearwater, 1978 February - November (Box 730)
    - Raymond Chambers and the Camberwell Collection, 1973 July - 1978 April (Box 730)
    - SPLIA Liason Committee, 1976 January - 1977 May (Box 730)
  - Sub-series 4.9: Irving Choban, 1974 (Box 730)
    There is only one folder.
    Irving Choban was heavily involved in the Long Island Historical Society/Brooklyn Historical Society. He served as the LIHS President of the Board of Directors from 1981 until 1984. Outside of that, he continued to serve on the board for many years, including supporting the name change to Brooklyn Historical Society. Choban is also responsible for donating both money and several items in the collections of what is today the Center for Brooklyn History. He had also served as the President of the Flatbush Historical Society for a number of years prior to serving on the board of LIHS.
    Irving Choban's papers consist of intra-institutional correspondence to and from LIHS members and the Board of Directors.
  - Sub-series 4.10: Susan Mullin, 1978-1991
    Susan Mullin's papers are arranged alphabetically by topic.
    Susan Mullin joined the Board of Directors in 1981. In June of 1985, Susan Mullin was voted to become the first female president of the Board of Directors in its entire history since it was established in 1863. Only a few months later in October of that same year the institution's name changed from Long Island Historical Society to Brooklyn Historical Society. With the name change, Mullin became not only the first female president of the new Brooklyn Historical Society, but the first president under a new name and mission. Susan Mullin stepped down from her role as President in 1990.
    Susan Mullin's papers include various amendments to the by laws, a museum conservation plan, and fundraising plans for the Shellens Gallery, as well as materials related to an antiques show.
    - ["Brooklyn Baseball and the Dodgers" exhibit correspondence], 1987 February (Box 730)
    - [Budget and curator planning], 1983 January (Box 730)
    - By-laws, 1983-1985 (Box 730)
      - Amendment, 1983 February
      - Amendment, 1985 April
      - Memos and drafts, 1985 October
      - Amendment, 1985 October
    - Museum conservation plan, 1986-1991 (Box 730)
    - Shellens Gallery fundraising, 1986-1989 (Box 730)
    - Antiques show, 1978-1983 (Box 729, Box 738, Box 739)
      Planning documents, advertisements and clippings, correspondence, invitations, committee documents, and financial records.
  - Sub-series 4.11: Carl Ferenbach III, 1994 (Box 729)
    Carl Ferenbach III served as the President of the Board of Directors of the Brooklyn Historical Soceity from 1990 until 1993. He also served as a member of the board both prior to and after his tenure as President.
    Carl Ferenbach's papers consist of an invitation to the 1994 Founders Ball.
  - Sub-series 4.12: Jessie Kelly, 1983-2007
    Jessie Kelly's papers are organized as Correspondence and Subject files. The correspondence is arranged chronologically. The subject files are arranged alphabetically.
    The bulk of Jessie Kelly's papers are subject files that were originally arranged according to topic. The bulk of the subject files are various BHS materials, such as the building renovation, grant funding, exhibitions, and by laws. The subject files also include other materials ranging from professional development to the Brooklyn Heights Association and the Flatbush Historical Society.
    Jessie Kelly's papers also include correspondence, which includes ingoing and outgoing correspondence from both internally within BHS and externally from other institutions. There is also a collection of outgoing correspondence that Jessie Kelly sent to various celebrities.
    - Correspondence, 2003-2005 (Box 716)
    - Subject files, 1983-2007 (Box 716, Box 717, Box 718, Box 719, Box 720, Box 721, Box 722)
  - Sub-series 4.13: Carol Clark, 1998-2003
    Carol Clark's papers are arranged alphabetically by topic.
    Carol Clark filled the position as head of the Brooklyn Historical Society from 1998 until her departure in 2001. Carol Clark is responsible for instigating the change in the title from Executive Director to President. The change was made official in a 1999 revision of the Society's by-laws. She was also the President of BHS during a major renovation that occurred from 1999 until 2003, after her departure. During this time, BHS operations were run out of an office in the MetroTech campus.
    Carol Clark's papers include materials related to insurance, the building renovation from the late 90s/early 00s, BHS exhibitions, correspondence, events, fundraising, NEH grants, staffing, and education programming.
    - AAM Directors and Officers Liability Insurance, 1999 January (Box 654)
    - Board of Education, 2001 July (Box 654)
    - [Brochures from Other Institutions], 1996-1999 (Box 654)
    - "Brooklyn at Play", 2000 April (Box 654)
    - Brooklyn Bridge Park Coalition, 1999 March - 2000 August (Box 654)
    - Brooklyn Discovery Center, 2000 June - October (Box 654)
    - Brooklyn History Fair, 1999 October (Box 654)
    - Brooklyn Walks, 1999 April - 2000 August (Box 654)
    - Brooklyn Works draft, 2001 May (Box 654)
    - BHS exhibition articles and awards, 2003 (Box 654)
    - C.W. Shaver, 1997-1998 (Box 654)
    - Capital Projects Campaign, 1998 September - 1999 July (Box 654)
    - Ceasar and Washburn Contract and Invoices, 1999 November - 2000 August (Box 654)
    - Celebration Dinner, 1999 April (Box 654)
    - Correspondence, 1998 September - 1999 December (Box 654)
    - DUMBO, 1999 June - July (Box 654)
    - East Hampton Library, 2000 July - August (Box 654)
    - Exhibition Department: Long Range Plan, 2001 May (Box 654)
    - "Famous Brooklynites", 1999 March (Box 654)
    - Fundraising, 1998 September - 1999 July (Box 655)
    - Jan Hird Pokorny Building Renovation, 1998-1999 (Box 655)
    - Leffers Homestead, 1999 March (Box 655)
    - [Leonard Goodstein Coney Island Collection], 1999 May - 2000 May (Box 655)
    - Making History Campaign, 2002 February (Box 655)
    - [Meeting Notes], 1998 January (Box 655)
    - Memorandum to Board of Trustees, 1999 January (Box 655)
    - Millennium Time Capsule, 1999 April - July (Box 655)
    - National Leadership Grant, Worklore: Brooklyn Voices Speak, 2001 November (Box 655)
    - NEH grant proposal and planning, 1999-2000 (Box 655)
    - Program Committee, 2000 April (Box 655)
    - [Robert A. M. Stern], 1999 September - November (Box 656)
    - Staffing Announcements and Job Listings, 1998 November - 1999 July (Box 656)
    - State Senator Velmanette Montgomery, 2000 August (Box 656)
    - Strategy Planning for Education Department, 2001 March (Box 656)
    - YWCA/YMCA, 2000 May - September (Box 656)
  - Sub-series 4.14: Gail S. Shaffer, 2001 (Box 729)
    This sub-series consists of newspaper clippings.
  - Sub-series 4.15: Deborah Schwartz, 1956-2020 (Box 690, Box 691, Box 692, Box 693, Box 694, Box 695, Box 696, Box 697, Box 698, Box 699, Box 700, Box 701, Box 702, Box 703, Box 704, Box 730)
    Deborah Schwartz's papers are arranged alphabetically by topic.
    Deborah Schwartz served as the President and CEO of the Brooklyn Historical Society from 2006 until 2020. Schwartz was serving in this position when BHS merged with the Brooklyn Public Library, and departed the institution after the merger was complete.
    Deborah Schwartz's papers include materials related to local politicians, BHS exhibitions, correspondence, grants including IMLS and NEH, press coverage, building renovations, auctions, other local institutions, fundraising, donations, legal materials, membership, state funding, president succession plans, records management, strategic planning, and staff materials.
    Some of Deborah Schwartz's papers are seemingly duplicates of materials from other series but kept with her sub-series both because they include notes and marginalia from Schwartz and to showcase the subjects and departments she was taking an active interest in while serving within her role as President and CEO.
- Series 5: Building records, 1866-2021
  This series has folder-level information on the back end. If researchers are in need of more detail, they should consult CBH staff.
  This series is arranged into eight sub-series:
  - Sub-series 5.1: Building Committee, 1866-1895
  - Sub-series 5.2: Building Plans, 1898-2013
  - Sub-series 5.3: Construction, 1866-1950
  - Sub-series 5.4: History, 1926-1984
  - Sub-series 5.5: Facilities, 1924-2020
  - Sub-series 5.6: Renovations, 1981-2012
  - Sub-series 5.7: Insurance, 2009-2013
  - Sub-series 5.8: BHS DUMBO, 2013-2017
  Series 5: Building records, 1866-2021, includes materials related to the building at 128 Pierrepont Street and the Brooklyn Historical Society's location in Empire Stores (BHS DUMBO). Materials include building plans, construction proposals, bids, and contracts, facility inspection reports, reports and articles related to the history of 128 Pierrepont, minutes and correspondence from the initial Building Committee that oversaw fundraising and early repair work, and insurance coverage documents.
  - Sub-series 5.1: Building Committee, 1866-1895 (Box 560, Box 565)
    This sub-series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
    Sub-series 5.1: Building Committee, 1866-1895, includes files kept by the Long Island Historical Society Building Committee regarding the building of 128 Pierrepont Street. There are also files regarding early repairs and work done on the building in the 1890s.
  - Sub-series 5.2: Building Plans, 1898 December - 2013 May (Folder OS Building Folders, Box 628, Box 629, Box 612, Box 566, Box 567, Box 568, Box 569)
    This sub-series is intellectually arranged chronologically, but physically arranged by size since these materials are oversize.
    Center for Brooklyn History holds the following related collections:
    - Long Island Historical Society building competition architectural drawings (ARC.302)
    Sub-series 5.2: Building Plans, 1898-2013, includes plans related to the building of and renovations to the Society's building at 128 Pierrepont Street.
    - [Storage vault diagram and water main map], 1977 (Box 629, Folder 10)
  - Sub-series 5.3: Construction, 1866-1950 (Box 625, Box 626)
    Sub-series 5.3: Construction, 1866-1950, includes materials related to the construction of the Long Island Historical Society's building at 128 Pierrepont Street.
  - Sub-series 5.4: History, 1926-1984 (Box 625)
    This sub-series is in original order.
    Sub-series 5.4: History, 1926-1984, includes articles and reports related to the history of the building at 128 Pierrepont Street.
  - Sub-series 5.5: Facilities, 1924-2020 (Box 559, Box 560, Box 561, Box 562, Box 563, Box 564, Box 565)
    This series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
    Sub-series 5.5: Facilities, 1924-2020, includes materials related to the installation, maintenance, and safety protocols of appliances, HVAC, elevator, electricity, plumbing, and other elements of the 128 Pierrepont Street building. Certificates of occupancy and inspection reports from the New York City Fire Department are also included in this sub-series.
  - Sub-series 5.7: Insurance, 2009-2013 (Box 627)
    This sub-series is arranged alphabetically by insurance company.
    Sub-series 5.7: Insurance, 2009-2013, includes materials related to various insurance converages. These include building insurance and insurance for collections materials.
    There are also insurance records in Series 16: Finance.
  - Sub-series 5.8: BHS DUMBO, 2013 - 2017 (Box 522, Box 523, Box 524, Box 569)
    This sub-series is arranged alphabetically by subject.
    Sub-series 5.8: BHS DUMBO, 2013-2017, includes materials related to the development of the Brooklyn Historical Society's Empire Stores location in DUMBO, also known as BHS DUMBO, which opened in 2017. Materials include plans, construction company contracts, appliance operations manuals, permits, leases with Empire Stores, and correspondence.
- Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1863-1977
  Materials in this sub-series are arranged chronologically.
  Series 6: Scrapbooks includes six Long Island Historical Society scrapbooks dating from 1863 to 1963. These scrapbooks document the Society's early activities through newspaper clippings, invitations, tickets, and other ephemera. The series also includes loose scrapbook pages primarily from the late 1960s to 1977, which largely consist of newspaper clippings. Additionally, there are two scrapbooks documenting the Society's natural history collection from 1876-1899.
  - LIHS scrapbooks, 1863-1963
    Bound scrapbooks of clippings and ephemera relating to the Long Island Historical Society and covering its first one hundred years of existence.
    - 1863-1868 (Box 613)
    - 1868-1877 (Box 614)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      This scrapbook is fragile and should be handled with care.
    - 1877-1883 (Box 615)
    - 1883-1894 (Box 616)
    - 1894-1942 (Box 617)
    - 1942-1963 (Box 618)
  - Natural history collection scrapbooks, 1876-1899 (Box 619, Box 620)
  - Loose scrapbook pages and ephemera, 1960-1977 (Box 621)
- Series 7: Curatorial Affairs and Collections, 1862-2020
  This series is arranged in the following sub-series:
  Sub-series 7.1: Administrative Files, 1889-2020
  Sub-series 7.2: Library Department Files, 1863-2019, bulk 1980-2007
  Sub-series 7.3: Librarian's Reports, 1874-1982, bulk 1890-1961
  Sub-series 7.4: Library Correspondence, 1862-1998
  Sub-series 7.5: Library Instruction, 2011-2014
  Sub-series 7.6: Cataloging and Access Projects, 1937-2019, bulk 1979-2013
  Sub-series 7.7: Collection Descriptions and Inventories, 1893-2015, bulk 1960-1999
  Sub-series 7.8: Collection Photography, 1974-1999
  Sub-series 7.9: Collections Care, 1959-2010, bulk 1973-2000
  Sub-series 7.10: Collections Committee, 1957-2019, bulk 1979-1985, 2009-2019
  Sub-series 7.11: Collections Move, 1995-2003
  Sub-series 7.12: Collections Sales, 1942-2011, bulk 1942-1981
  Sub-series 7.13: Curatorial Department Files, 1980-2011, bulk 1984-2007
  Sub-series 7.14: Deaccessioning Program, 1980-1998, bulk 1991-1998
  Sub-series 7.15: Grant Files, 1971-2016, bulk 1981-2008
  Sub-series 7.16: Public History Department Files, 2011-2017
  Sub-series 7.17: Students and Faculty in the Archives (SAFA), 2010-2015
  Sub-series 7.18: Incoming Loans, 1972-2009
  Sub-series 7.19: Outgoing Loans, 1900-2014
  Folders that contain physical audiovisual media are noted at the file level.
  Additional material concerning the Society's library and curatorial work can be found in the following series:
  Series 8: Exhibitions and Special Projects
  Series 9: Oral History
  Series 7: Curatorial Affairs and Collections contains records produced by the library, curatorial, and public history departments of the Brooklyn Historical Society. This material documents major cataloging and access projects, reference work, collection sales, deaccessioning, successful and unsuccessful grant applications, incoming and outgoing loans, collection descriptions and inventories, and collections care. The series also includes policies, procedures, and guides for managing and providing access to the collections.
  - Sub-series 7.1: Administrative Files, 1889-2020
    Materials in this sub-series are arranged in rough chronological order by creation date.
    Sub-series 7.1: Administrative Files contains materials related to the management of collections across the library and museum departments. Included are policies, procedures, forms, long-range and strategic planning documentation, guides, handbooks, manuals, collections management research, and budgets and other expense information.
    - Account of Books in Librarian's Room, 1889 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Records of Material Sent to Skidmore, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      This file contains inventories and correspondence related to the collection material sent to Skidmore College for safekeeping during World War II. The materials were sent in May 1942 and returned in October 1944.
    - Estimates [Invoices], 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Estimates [Invoices], 1952, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - LIHS Acknowledgement of Gift Forms, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Long Island Historical Society Policies and Practices, circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Insurance, 1960 October (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Records of Staff, 1940-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - Library Operations, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Directory of Library Stacks, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Restricted Funds, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Acquisition Policy, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Cataloging Procedures, 1971-1977 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Fine Arts Committee, 1976-1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Location Guide, 1978 August (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Accession Catalogue Worksheets, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Agreement for Incoming Loan Forms, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Agreement for Outgoing Loan Forms, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Application for Research Use of the Society's Archives, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - [Collection Guide List], circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Condition Report Forms, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Deed of Gift Forms, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Facilities Report / Loan Info Sheet, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Form Letter to Accompany Loan Condition Reports, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Genealogy Cataloging Procedures, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Guide to Genealogical Research in the Brooklyn Historical Society, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Fine Arts Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Fine Arts Committee, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - [Guide to House and Neighborhood Research], circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 1)